[seagulls squawking]
♪ [music] ♪
[car honks]
[Mac] If you ever get to the States,
give me a call.
Oh, thank you very much.
[waves splashing]
Breakfast ready, Gordon?
[Gordon] We have a problem.
What?
[Gordon] The beach-- Ben's beach.
What's the problem?
[Gordon] The problem is
that really is Ben's beach.
He owns the shoreline,
four miles of it
from the grass down to the low tide mark.
I found it in the parish records
when I was checking on some title deeds.
[Mac] Can he prove it?
[Gordon] We can't steal the beach
from him, it's his.
We'll have to buy it from him.
♪ [music] ♪
Aberdeendshire. 2010.
[Reporter] Donald Trump
has arrived in Scotland to talk
about his plans for what he claims
will be the world's greatest golf course.
[Reporter] The way Donald Trump
swept into the Northeast on his
usual wave of publicity.
His private jet touched down
at Aberdeen airport,
just after 10 o'clock this morning.
[Reporter] Earlier amidst protesters
who have bought small plots of land
have become a bit of a block,
the controversial development.
[Reporter] Michael Forbes is of course,
the farmer who refuses to sell to Trump.
[Michael Forbes] It's my home.
I've stayed here for 43 years now
and he won't put me out it.
[Reporter] Mr. Trump said,
the development could still go ahead
without the farmer's land.
[Donald Trump] Because if we build a
300 or 400-million dollar hotel,
I don't think you want the windows
looking down into a slum.
[Reporter] While Donald Trump will
be here for two days,
he says he'll be examining every
square foot to make sure
his final designs are perfect.
♪ You'll know, when's time to go on ♪
♪ You'll really want to grow
and grow till tall ♪
♪ They all, in the end, will fall ♪
[wind blowing]
♪ [music] ♪
[rooster crowing].
[Molly Forbes] I usually get up
about seven and let the cat out.
And in these dark mornings,
I just nip back to bed again
and turn on the TV and lie
till about half past seven,
get ready, start my porridge.
Yes, that's for the hens.
Sometimes, I keep out-- if I'm going
to have something with tatties,
I keep out a couple for myself.
[laughs]
They are very good tatties.
Just nearly there.
Before I used to count
and the fox just nipped up the lot.
♪ [music] ♪
[Radio] I wanna ask a question
about, in regard to...
It's all talking on
that station and the fox thinks
there's people about because they--
they don't like people.
[laughs]
That's just lovely.
Ah, old ladies.
And an egg.
[Anthony Baxter] How many do you
get a day?
[Molly] Oh, well, sometimes two,
sometimes one, sometimes none.
♪ [music] ♪
MEDIA LAUNCH, MENIE ESTATE
Site of proposed Trump Golf Resort
I'm sure you know guys,
be mindful of yourselves.
Don't rush forward like idiots.
You can get all the shots you want.
Mr. Trump will spend time with you
afterwards as well.
[cameras clicking]
If you spread out, guys,
you'll get the best view.
The bagpipers are gonna stay.
♪ [bagpipe music] ♪
They've divided the Marquee
into two sections.
Park section next door were like,
you know, fancy laced tablecloths,
and what have you
and we're getting coffee, tea.
[cameras clicking]
[Donald Trump] Hello, everybody.
[male] I don't believe this.
- [Donald] Good.
And everyone knows Martin Hawtree,
uh-huh.
He's the architect of the site.
How are you?
Nice to see you.
[male] Thank you.
[Sarah Malone] This is the top man
from Scottish Television.
Very good.
Scottish Television. Very-- I like that.
One of the papers had headlines:
"Trump Met By Protestors,"
Two people and a dog.
The dog was the one I was afraid of.
[laughing]
The dog looked vicious actually.
[male guest] The dog looked
intelligent.
[male guest] Exactly.
I'll see you guys later.
[Molly] I was born on the farm
that I worked on during the war,
but I wasn't brought up on that farm
because my father, well,
see a lot of driver-- well, he was actually
a ploughman in his younger day.
There's a ploughing match.
You know, my father did ploughing.
That's my father.
He was a prized plougher, my father.
He has lots of cups and medals.
We used to go and watch them.
I know my father's style of ploughing.
See how he is, look!
See he's super bent.
This is where we lived.
That's the shop at Whitkerrins,
which is no more
and there's the Daniel's buses.
My eyes are not as good
as they used to be.
When I was here first,
it was March, we saw them.
And then last year, just February,
that's two there.
That used to come every year
and we knew it was the same two
because of his long neck.
They're beautiful birds.
[male guest] Really beautiful. I think we should--
Really beautiful.
I'm shaking hands with you.
[laughing]
I said-- she should work for us.
Ms. Scotland, come here a minute.
So, you won't be going to
the Ms. Universe pageant and--
and-- who's going, who's going?
How do you rate her?
[Nicola] She's good.
- Good?
Yeah.
- [Donald] Do you think she's good?
[Donald] Does she have your beauty?
Oh, I don't know.
I think so.
[giggles]
[Donald] I doubt it.
Are you from this area?
[Nicola] From Glasgow.
That's not so bad.
That's close enough.
Close enough.
She's beautiful.
Thank you.
She may want to work
for sales and stuff.
Okay?
Yeah.
♪ [bag pipe music] ♪
[Donald] There's so many familiar faces
from the press.
They've really been amazing
supporters of the project.
This is really the circle
of our friends.
This was really a celebration
of our friends,
a celebration of people
that supported us.
It was spectacular for me yesterday
to be able to walk the final version
of the course, with my father to say,
you know, this is now what we're doing,
this is what will be etched
into this land forever.
As Lord Provost of the City,
yesterday it was my pleasure
to welcome these two gentlemen
who will look at the plans
that you've got produce this absolutely,
outstanding golf course.
The excitement in this is absolutely,
outstandingly wonderful.
[cameras continue clicking]
[Donald] Any questions, gentlemen?
- Very nice questions.
[reporter] Mr. Trump, what would you say
to the many local residents here
who feel that you've run roughshod over,
planning legislation
and environmental issues
simply because you've got
lots of money?
It's a very interesting question
because honestly,
this is a very popular project.
We've had great support from the Council
and great support
from the political leaders.
We've saved the dunes and from
an environmental standpoint,
it's a much better situation than it was
before we bought the site.
You can sometimes see
the deer, you know,
coming out of these trees across there.
They jump the fence, no problem.
They're so beautiful.
I know they're wild,
but they're not too scared.
You know, they-- they just
seem to put up with us.
[reporter] Just a little back swing--
that would do us.
You want me to face forward?
[reporter] Yeah, yeah that's great.
- Watch this.
[Anthony] What was the first
thing he said to you?
Eh, give this man
a job, he says.
Give this man a job
and I've got a job.
Then he kept saying it.
Three times, he said it.
Give this man a job.
I said, I've got a bloody job.
I don't want a job.
[laughs]
Keep this short, ladies and gentlemen,
the rain is coming.
[Donald] Give me an umbrella.
[reporter] Does calling Mr. Forbes
and his property names...
...how does that help?
No, I'm just-- you see,
I happen to be a very truthful person.
His property is terribly maintained.
It's slum-like,
it's disgusting.
He's got stuff thrown
all over the place.
He lives like a pig and I did say that
and I'm an honest guy
and I speak honestly.
And I think that's why
some people like me
and some people probably
don't like me,
but I think he'd do himself
a great service,
if he fixed up his property.
And I'm not talking money.
It's not a question of money.
It's a question of a little
manual labor.
[male voice] Huh,
Trump says he did a deal twice.
That's right.
I'd seen that.
I said, what a load of
frigging lies, I said.
I said, it explains what's
hanging over on the shed.
I said, just go look at that.
I said, you have that compulsive liar.
That's what I say to that.
[reporter] Mr. Trump, if you have a message
for Michael Forbes this afternoon...
...what would it be?
No, I have no message.
[reporter] Do you quite enjoy it
and feel that in the end,
your power and money
will win over anyway?
No, I don't-- I don't
feel it's power and money.
I think that principle will win out,
but my people made deals with him
on two occasions.
My representatives have absolutely
made two deals that he broke,
so he knows that.
His people know that,
whoever his people may be.
[male] You'll see it in the paper
if you get it today,
his face is right on
the bloody front page.
[male] Why does he need us for his hotel?
Oh, because he doesn't want
people looking out and seeing a tip.
I see.
$$- Aye, that's his excuse now.
Oh, well, nobody's complained
about it up to now, eh?
He passed us this morning
and just flew on in
his top of the range Range Rover,
the black tint windows.
Oh,I missed getting a super photo
of him the first time he arrived here.
The wind forced him on the escarpment
and I thought that the press
would have loved that.
I could have sold that picture
for a fortune.
His hair was sticking out like that.
You know, the whole locker thing,
it had come off, where it's all
one round and was out to a point.
Damn it.
This is my husband's
hat aboard this boat.
He was Chief Petty Officer on deck.
It's a bit dusty.
[Susan Munro] There he is.
Look, under the red umbrella.
It really is just now,
which is just there looking
slightly to the right,
is where he was hoping
to put in the clubhouse
and where he was going to put it in,
it tends to flood because
the water overruns down
off the land to there,
so you'll have difficulty putting
a clubhouse there
unless it's on stilts.
[Molly] My father,
he sang songs that you never
heard of today and he used
to sing a song,
"You'll never miss the water
until the well runs dry,"
which is a very true saying in that.
[water streaming]
♪ [music] ♪
[Martin Ford] It really shouldn't
matter, if the applicant
is Mother Theresa of Calcutta,
and she wants to carry out
development in order to raise money,
to help the sick or indeed,
even if it's Donald Trump.
The permission isn't to the person,
it's to the land.
[applause]
[Martin] Too much money makes
your head go funny.
It's a 21st Century
Highland Clearance.
[applause]
[announcer] I now like to welcome
a representative from the Green Party
to the stage,
local councilor, Martin Ford.
[cheering and applause]
[Martin] Thank you very much.
For those of you who don't know
in Aberdeenshire,
we have a council who gives Donald Trump
everything he asks for,
and can't make up their minds
whether to throw people
out of their homes to help him.
[Martin] Firstly, I think
it's important for people,
not from the Northeast of Scotland,
to have some sense of the buildup.
March 2006
In 2006, I think that was
the first official state visit
by Mr. Trump to Scotland.
[Male Reporter] His plan is for the
Menie Estate at Balmedie, near Aberdeen.
On it, he will create
two golf courses,
a 450-bedroom hotel and housing,
as well as holiday apartments
and golf villas, an investment
of a billion pounds.
November 2007
[Female reporter] Multimillion-pound
golf resort in Aberdeenshire is rejected.
The chairman of a committee
of Aberdeenshire councilors
used his casting vote after
a three-hour meeting was deadlocked.
All the parties had committed themselves
to sustainable development
and you could apply the test
of sustainable development to
the Trump proposal and he failed them.
He failed them in spades.
[Female Reporter] The Trump
organization has confirmed
it will now pull out of Scotland
after a bitter rejection at Balmedie.
We are very disappointed.
Ultimately, we can go and develop
the project somewhere else.
We'll be fine.
I think it's the people of Aberdeen
and the Shire that were really let down
by their council today.
[Martin] It was predicated on
long distance tourism.
It was predicated on people flying
across the Atlantic,
to play a few games of golf
and flying back across the Atlantic.
It was predicated on utilizing
an irreplaceable
and diminishing resource of
effectively natural habitat.
[Female Reporter] Mr. Trump
also reiterated his concern
about a proposal to build
an offshore wind farm
close to his site.
When I look out
onto the ocean from the 18th hole
of Trump International Golf Links,
to be honest with you,
I wanna see the ocean.
I don't want to see windmills.
December 2007
Good evening.
There's a renewed hope tonight that
American tycoon, Donald Trump's plans
for a one billion pounds golf development
in Aberdeenshire, will go ahead.
In a dramatic twist, the Scottish
government have called in
the controversial planning application,
taking it out of
Aberdeenshire Council's hands.
[Reporter] Never before has an
application been called in,
in this manner.
[Martin Ford] By calling in
an application
that had already been refused,
it's inescapable that the government
has in some way expressed a view that
it does not want the application refused.
October 2008
♪ [music] ♪
[reporter] Today, almost
two years on,
from when he first announced
his proposals,
the Scottish governments have given
the Tycoon, the green light.
Well, I think
the message would be,
I'm going to build for the people
of Scotland,
the greatest golf course
anywhere in the world.
There'll be nothing like it
and it's going to be done
environmentally perfect.
[reporter] The Menie Estates
is in the constituency
of First Minister Alex Salmond.
The balance of
opinion among people
in the Northeast of Scotland,
among my constituents,
is very strongly in favor.
And that's because we can see the--
the social and economic benefits.
I mean 6000 jobs across Scotland,
1400 local and permanent jobs
here in the Northeast of Scotland,
that's a very powerful argument
and I think that outweighs
the environmental concerns.
There's not many people
looking to invest a billion pounds
in this local economy.
It's right in keeping
with our development strategy
the inward bound tourism
is key for the city in Shire.
That's what we're here to support.
And in partnership with Mr. Trump,
I believe we can do that together.
I thought it was
the biggest thing that did happen
in the Northeast since oil
was discovered.
October 2009
[Protestors] No, no CPO!
You will be the next to go!
No, no CPO!
[Martin] Early in 2009,
Mr. Trump's legal people
approached the council with
suggestions as to how they might
justify the councilors,
the use of compulsory purchase.
[Female Reporter] The Trump
organization have asked the council
to consider using CPOs and councilors
decided it was inappropriate to reject
the use of compulsory purchase orders
without a full report.
All it does is it
leaves a big cloud over our heads.
That's all it does.
Disappointment mixed
with fury to be quite honest.
This is an action of people
with no conscience and no will power.
This is typical of this
sort of thing that we get.
Oh, it's very typical.
It's very typical for councilors
like yourself to de--
to defer decisions
that are critical to people's
livelihoods and you failed.
Unfortunately that--
- You failed.
[Donald Trump, Jr.] I'm thrilled
with the outcome.
They continue to diminish
the importance
and nonsensical motions
put forth by Mr. Ford
and hopefully, this will be
the last few minutes
of his political career because
I think he's blown virtually,
everything he's ever touched.
[Martin] Since that time,
the residents of many
in their own homes, have been living
with a threat of a possibility
that they would be forced
to leave them against their will.
Local Hero (1983)
Just bang in the window.
Jesus, how do you do business
with someone who doesn't have a door?
[knocking]
I look at his place
and it's a pig sty.
Do I regret that?
No, I don't regret that.
It's a pig sty.
It turns out actually,
we've got a collection
of remarkable, principled people,
who have recognized
what's right and what's wrong
and have said,
they're not standing for wrong.
Ben, what we wanted to ask you,
have you ever thought about moving?
No. You see, the thing is,
I'm still working the place myself.
It's my living.
♪ [music] ♪
[Michael] All my relations
have been salmon fishing all their lives.
My great grandfather, my grandfather,
my father, all my uncles,
they're all salmon fishers
and it's just in the blood, you know.
You just have to do it.
I was 14-1/2, took fishing
with my uncle when I left school.
I worked with him for a few years
then I went trolling.
Everybody knew everybody, you know.
All the salmon fishers knew everybody.
It was great.
It was cotton nets back then.
It rotted quick
so they make a lot of nets.
These new ones, all made of plastic,
polythene, they last a lot longer
rather than later, you know.
So, you needed a full crew
to work the old nets, you know.
That boat that size, you'd have needed
probably six- six men to pull
one of these nets up, but now
you can do it with two, you know.
[boat engine running]
We used to fish for mackerel
off Tarbet Hill.
Still plenty of lobsters on the go,
is there?
They've just come on.
Pretty sacks for those,
still that's just the start of them.
♪ Reyni að grafa upp og ♪
♪ hjartgæsku og raun ♪
[Michael Forbes] Well, I still
am fishing.
I haven't done it for
the last couple of years
because of-with my back,
but I'll get going again next year.
♪ Reyni að bora á ♪
I have to tow my boat down to the beach.
It's not like here
you come out of a harbor.
I have to launch it off the beach,
and well, I've nets on the beach,
state nets, you know.
and I'll be touring on course
through his golf course as well
'coz that's how we do it.
We used to do it on golfs.
We don't lift them when it
trails out and things.
I'm looking forward to it.
[laughs]
A lot of local people
don't see Michael
as a particular problem.
They see him as someone who's standing up
for what is rightfully his
and they don't believe all the clap trap
that Trump's PR machine put out
about a hardnosed farmer.
You know, he's standing up
for what's his.
Why shouldn't he? Why wouldn't he,
you know?
This is actually zone for the housing.
On the crest of that hill
between David Milne's property,
there is going to be
the eight-storey blocks
of time share apartments.
My house originally
a coast guard station built in 1954,
but there's been a station here
since about 1860 something.
There's a row of five cottages
here to my right.
They are Coast guard cottages.
The occupants were originally
workers in the Coast Guard.
So if when you look at the drawings,
you see something that looks like
a crashed space shuttle.
That's the hotel.
And where my home is,
is meant to be a car park.
The buildings that you see
just a little further over there,
the other side of the green field,
that's Mike Forbes' place.
Again, under threat
of compulsory purchase.
Down below here, there's white building,
that's the home of the Munro family.
Again, under compulsory purchase threat.
Well, no compulsory
purchase.
No more Trump lies on
the top of the postcard.
The who's down the road to the dunes,
where once you could roam free.
♪ [music] ♪
Well, I've been here a long time, near
on three decades, that's a long time.
Most of my adult life's
been spent in this house.
Brought my family up here.
Finley was born here.
There he is.
Here is pets, hi pets.
And then this man, this foreigner comes in
because he's got a few pounds
to reckon in his pocket,
a bit of a name,
and we're just cast aside.
We're in the way and I think it's
an awful way to treat people.
That was just when we moved here,
I was expecting Finley.
He was, as I said, born here, so...
as you can see the difference
from my few years.
This was taken an excess of 25 years ago,
me with the children
and my mother paddling.
Oh, it was just glorious.
You realized what you've got
and what's going to be taken away.
[Mickey] I got a crew in bay.
Maybe I should take the cruise
up in the old Zodi.
♪ He's in love with rock n' roll, whoo ♪
♪ He's in love with getting stoned whoo ♪
♪ He's in love with Janie Jones, whoo ♪
When I just left art college in 1974,
I moved to London and this is where
I continued my relationship with,
at that time John Miller,
who most people know as Joe Strummer.
♪ And he knows what he got to do ♪
♪ He knows he's gotta have fun with you ♪
Having extricated myself
from the music industry,
I've had a chance to meet Kim,
my partner.
It must have been worst yesterday because
the winds were terrific yesterday.
It's a bit rough today, ain't it?
So they're taking you out
to the water then?
[waves splashing]
I used to come up here
with my grandmother and my aunt
and my cousins on the bus
from Aberdeen in the mid-50s
with their bandy catchers and playing
commandos on those dunes.
It was a fantastic open space within
reach of ordinary people from Aberdeen
and the only wall stretched has been
swirled up by this developer.
Now, that is primarily what drives me
to say, it shouldn't happen.
♪ You, you ♪
It's a real
mosaic of habitat.
You've got everything from open sand
to shrubs, to trees, to wetlands.
A green Scotland is effectively a myth
if something like this is allowed
to happen and lots of areas are either
destroyed moved around and sanitized,
disturbed and there'll be
a few bits left scattered around
as a kind of mitigation
of this development.
This very damaging two golf course
development, the whole package is wrong.
♪ I wonder if I'm alone ♪
♪ Just ever to me ♪
[water splashing]
Welcome to our little world, McIntyre.
This is a bit of a loo.
And this hard-- look here,
is an actual flop
blasting in the underground tank.
♪ [music] ♪
Incredibly steep,
isn't it?
[machine beeping]
These sorts of models give us
mindful clues
to understand the interaction
of waves on beaches,
the interactions of beach
and the upper beach
and then the available if it's sand
to be brought into sand dune systems,
such as we've got in
the Aberdeenshire coast.
In many, what we've got is a
very, very clear model of sand
moving in the northerly direction,
crystal clear, that is very interesting
and from the point of view science,
from point of view of understanding
how our landscapes adjust
to climate change.
It's the only one left and once we've
lost the only one left,
we'll be dealing with essentially
artificial systems
and the problem with artificial systems,
of course, is that because we've
meddled with them in some way,
we don't actually know what
the former track might be.
These are tees that are built
onto very steep sand dunes,
so they will have to be built up
artificially by movement of sand
from elsewhere in the site.
Up to eight meters vertically
will have to be in placed,
and that will involve moving biblical
amounts of sand from A to B.
So not only do you lose the natural
dynamism that this area
is noted for scientifically,
you will stabilize it,
so you'll lose the dynamism but also
you'll be constructing
a largely artificial
sand dune environment.
[Donald] Well, I've stabilized
the dunes and that means the dunes
will be with us forever and that's good
because dunes can be gone with the wind.
I mean dunes can move in shift
and sometimes, they do,
but when you stabilize them,
they're with you forever.
So, I've stabilized them and ultimately,
I think that's going to be a great factor
and a great thing for Scotland
and for Aberdeen.
These wilderness
environments are equivalent if you like
of the Amazon rain forest
or the swamps in South America.
And many of these wilderness environments
have been lost around the world
and in Britain, we've got very,
very few of those left.
And what's happening here is that
we're losing yet another.
We've had
tremendous support
from the environmental groups and--
so I'm very happy about that.
I mean we've had great,
great environmental support.
I received many environmental
awards over the years.
I think the greatest thing
I've ever done for the environment is,
what I'll be doing right here
in Aberdeen,
but when we went to our meetings,
we had tremendous support
from major environmentalists
and environmental groups.
Is my hair okay?
It's blown all over.
[Emily] Have a look in the lens.
I can't see it.
Do you have a mirror?
Emily, give me a mirror.
[Dr. Hansom] There are no
environment organizations
that I know of that favor this at all.
[Donald] Who has a mirror?
[Dr. Hansom] RSPB opposed it.
The SIPA, the Scottish environment,
the protection agency,
Scottish Natural Heritage, were
violently opposed to this development
and a lot of wildlife trust
were against the development
and the Rambler's Association
were against the development.
I know of no credible
environmental organization
that favored such a development
on the environment.
♪ [music] ♪
This is an accolade site, a site
of special scientific interest.
The highest conservation accolade
that this country can bestow
and yet we allow a golf course
to be developed upon it,
which will remove the scientific
interest completely
and it's something of a personal
tragedy and great sadness,
across the scientific community.
Summer. Construction begins
Trump Golf Course No.1
♪ [music] ♪
[Susan] It is alarming.
Well, look what security
did to me long time ago.
It came out of nowhere, stopped my car,
hands on bonnets and I got scared.
They're saying that's for
the lorries let in.
The cars and pickups everything
can still use our road.
Look, we've got a gap
in the trees already.
Well, those trees are seemingly coming
down which they shouldn't be taken down.
It's hard to Mike Forbes. That's where -
they're spring is up in these trees.
If we don't make through them,
we'll have a look.
I haven't been down Mike's this week.
Oh, God. Lord it--
It looks like nobody is in, is there?
Do with it, but the water,
and Moira, David Milne's wife,
she had a dream that she woke up
one morning and we were disappeared.
We were all underwater.
And I said, "Oh."
She said, I'd looked out the window
and you were gone.
All I could see was water.
She had a premonition.
I said, "Well, don't say that, Moira."
Me, Mike and you are gonna have
problems with your water.
We're really horrified to see this bank.
I mean what is it?
I think it's a road
and that trees are coming down.
This is absolutely horrendous.
That will be the end of the spring.
[truck engines running]
[Security] Who you with?
[Anthony Baxter] I'm a freelance.
[Security] As all the rest of
the press, anyone who comes in here
would have the--do you wanna turn that off
or do you wanna leave that on or...
[Anthony Baxter] I'm just going
to leave it on, yeah.
[Security] Yeah?
[Security] I'm sure you're well aware.
We've had a lot of damage here.
[Anthony Baxter] Who's causing
the damage here.
[Security] No, no, no, no.
I'm only--
I'm only just putting you in the picture.
[Anthony Baxter] You know, I'm just
basically overlooking from this bank,
there shouldn't be any health or safety
considerations, should there?
[Security] No, no, no, no.
There isn't, but again, I would--
I would ask you to announce
yourself to the site.
It's the wish of the clients or
if you wish to film on site,
we've no issue with it at all.
You know, there's no problem.
[Man in truck] Who are you with?
- [Anthony Baxter] Sorry?
[security] Who are you with?
[Anthony Baxter] I'm just
freelance, yeah.
[security] The police want
to have a word with you.
[Anthony Baxter] Hi, there.
- [Police] What are you doing down here?
[Anthony Baxter] Just doing
a bit of filming.
[Police] If you're a freelancer,
are you filming for yourself or
are you filming for one?
[Anthony Baxter] Yeah, just filming
for myself.
[Police] There's a lot of publicity
here a bit, you can see that should...
[Anthony Baxter] Yeah.
[Police] And a lot of this area through here
require a warranty.
[Anthony Baxter] Yeah.
[Police] So for health
and safety reasons,
you should really be contacting
the department. This is a state line.
[Anthony Baxter] Right, yeah, but for--
- [Police] The-- the access to woods.
[Anthony Baxter] There's not a sort of
right to roam as there not in Scotland?
[Police] There is but not
within vehicle-- vehicles.
[Anthony Baxter] But I wasn't in
a vehicle, sir. I was standing.
[Police 1] But again, it's--
[Police 2] Excuse me one second.
- [Anthony Baxter] Uhm?
[Police 2] Can you switch off
your camera off, please?
[Mickey Foote] Of course, you
can't cut across the dunes now,
because they built this road.
That's the road they built
that they've dozed across the--
the natural drainage,
so they're trapping more so,
all over the place.
Look, look at that.
Yes, it goes up and down
with the tide, all this stuff.
[Susan] Hello. How are you?
[Mickey] Hi, there. How are you?
It's horrific that water.
[Susan] Yeah, but they
virtually dammed us
and the Putinati Road.
[Mickey] My concern is
where they're gonna pump it to?
[Walter Forbes] Trees suck up water,
that's why the trees are planted.
Now, they've cut the trees away
and bury them in a hole.
They took them away
and buried them in a hole.
Dug a big hole over the bank here.
They took all the trees and put them
in a hole and buried them.
[laughing]
According to my neighbor, he says there's
400 trees that they buried over there.
[Susan] And as we go down
the corner, Anthony,
if you keep looking ahead you will see
are little--
the little forest here
has now disappeared.
I came home and my son said to me,
"Oh, mom, all the trees are gone."
Oh, me. Modern grass being stripped
into blocks, taken away in huge dumpers
and as you can see
from the last time we were here,
there's been vast quantity of sand taken.
I just can't believe it.
It'd be interesting to see
if where all the sand's coming from?
[Walter Forbes] That's the sand
dunes up driving.
There's some of the dunes from
over there above, but not here.
I didn't think they were
allowed to move them.
Susan Munro is given
a camera to record changes.
[Anthony] That should be
on now, here.
Listen and then you just press that,
that button there.
Yeah, the one
in the right.
Yeah.
So, I'm filming.
Oh, well.
♪ [music] ♪
To come here everyday, you really get an
idea of the destruction that's happening.
Also noticed there doesn't seem
to be anybody coming down,
checking on anything.
There's not anybody.
They never see us.
the only person you ever see is
security keeping--
keeping people away really.
Three weeks later.
[Susan Munro] I don't know where I am.
You would think we were on a beach.
Not in a beautiful, dynamic
dune system has totally gone.
All we can see is flattened dunes.
Sand everywhere.
[Donald] I look at Mr. Forbes
and his disgusting conditions
in which he lives and that people
have to look at that
and it's about time
that somebody spoke out.
It's almost like in fact,
it is like a slum-like condition.
For people to have to look at this
virtual slum is a disgrace.
Mr. Forbes is not a man that people
in Scotland should be proud of.
[engine running]
Mr. Forbes is not a respected man
among the people that he lives with.
I mean people have come up to us.
They've written us notes.
They've written us letters
that this guy is all sorts of things
and I won't say it.
They're saying it.
Mr. Forbes lives in a
pig-like atmosphere. It's disgusting.
They're a lovely,
genuine, honest, authentic people.
And they're really sincere people.
And yeah, absolute pleasure to--
to be involved in a project with them.
[Michael] David McCue, he's an
artist and he got in touch with me,
asking me if it would be okay
if he did an art exhibition.
I said, "Yeah, if you like, yeah."
So, I said we'll do it in a Marquee tent out here,
but he wasn't for that.
He had to have it in that shed there.
Why? I don't know, but he
had to have it in that shed.
[laughing]
The worst shed I've got and he had
to have it in that.
[laughing]
I think we'll just
stick with that for just now.
Can we rip it off?
- All right.
Yeah.
[David] I loved the barn because
the minute it started to change in
and put things in there, it kind of--
the re-contextualized the work
in exactly the way I hoped it would do.
I knew that.
[David] Give back everything
that they took away.
It was great meeting
Michael's wife, Sheila.
[Sheila] Chrissie, what the hell
do you think you're doing?
[David McCue] She's really feisty
and has a great sense of humor,
a great sense of who she is,
her own kind of identity.
She doesn't choose to sometimes be
at the limelight, but other times,
I think it's important
to hear her voice, too.
The drawing represents as a metaphor
for behind every successful man,
there's a strong woman.
[brids chirping]
I really wanted to find for myself
what the trift was,
at what's happening at that site,
like the security presence for instance
and that was really stressful for Sheila
and Michael and Molly as well.
You know, that's their homes
and there'd be just a vehicle
that would circle their lands and stop,
pause and then move off again,
but it's intimidating and I certainly
felt like that the week that I was there.
This one for me was very much--
that's a very typical Trump stance
and pose that he does very often
and it's almost like a trademark,
the way he gestures and his body language
and obviously referenced
were whole, quite considerably
with the repeat pattern
of the dollar sign
that's like a brick wall.
You've hit a brick wall day to day,
it's kind of scenario.
The media has been coming down to us,
this place that's been talking about it
as a slum, which it certainly isn't.
And to be able to sort of show off
the interior of that barn,
which they've only just seen
the exterior of,
and get a real glimpse into the history,
of the heritage of this space.
A glimpse sight of the back square that
looks on to all of the other properties,
which are in a similar position of maybe
coming under compulsory purchase.
It was just-- it was perfect.
Twenty thumbs up on a hobby.
[laughing]
[applause]
[Michael] It's in grossly
bad taste, which of course, is spot on.
[laughing]
[indistinct chattering]
[David] I really wanted it
to be an act of peace.
That was quite important.
That they weren't just passively,
you know, looking at pieces of work.
[cheering and applause]
[Michael Forbes] I've seen some
of them in the computer,
David's computer but they don't look
the same in the computer.
[Martin] Once again,
there's a very pleasant atmosphere
while this is a very serious business,
it's great to see members of the
community coming together like this
in support of the local residents.
[Michael Forbes] My father
was a salmon fisher.
What's that?
[Michael] When I was born,
I was born in a beach here.
Uh-huh.
And then we moved to Whiteadder River,
a couple of mile to Milan infantry,
Uh-huh.
Then he got a job in Tarland,
so we moved in to Aberdeen
and it was Aberdeen, I was 14-1/2
and I had enough of Aberdeen.
Uh-huh.
And I came here and worked
with my uncle when I left school.
[indistinct chattering]
[Walter Forbes] I got to get near
for the kids, but they're--
they're chicken though,
they're throwing underneath through it.
[laughing]
[Mickey Toole] The Trump paintings,
they-- it says very much on the red,
the anger whereas, Michael's
very much the cool blue
and the relaxed greens.
That reflect the diversity
of where they come from
and what they mean,
what they're intentions are, you know?
I think these intentions are very angry,
very self-motivated,
very self-interested.
The way they display their wealth
and their attitude, you know.
It is very much a contrast
about what goes on, here.
But you would expect that.
I mean he's an international figure
and Michael was a very local figure.
He's very much appreciated by his
local friends and people who know him.
[Susan Munro] A lot of the local
people here,
certainly, a lot more
down to life, you know?
I think that living in
the real world, you know?
And it just shows you, you know,
the support we have reigned about.
Absolute biased and in favor of Trump.
- [Michael Forbes] Aye, aye.
Absolute.
- [Michael Forbes] Oh, aye.
And reporting his negative,
I mean destructive comments
about you and it's very
personal, isn't it?
[Michael Forbes] I know, I know.
Flying about is the most extravagant
thing and building a property
and golf development here to
attract to American golfers is,
is just contrary to environmental
way of life that we will have to lead.
[David McCue] As a personal gift
to Michael and Sheila and--
and you know, it feels important for me
to give something to them
for all the help that they've given me.
Like all my paintings, I find it
very difficult to talk about it
in its early stages and well,
it's going to be an image of Michael
and on the salmon fishing port.
♪ Reyni að grafa upp og hjartgæsku og ♪
♪ Reyni að brjótast inn ♪
♪ Reyni að bora á, og saga hengilásinn ♪
Four weeks later.
[water streaming]
[Susan Munro] It was a Saturday and
Michael was washing the Land Rover
and he also washed Sheila's car
and then the hose went to a trickle
and he says, “Oh, well,
what a shilly off.”
So, he came over and said to me,
"Be canny, we have water because
I think it's going off."
[Michael Forbes] You see
that line of trees?
Well, just as that ends here,
well, that's where my well is.
Well, it's a spring, a common well.
As you could see the lorry
is going over there,
there's no-- they built the
road on top of my spring.
[truck beeping]
Well, I think my water is more important
than his bloody road just now,
but not to them, eh?
I found out but, they just keep saying
that they're gonna fix it.
I'm still waiting.
You think they've got priority.
Here, see, there's no water.
Dry.
[Anthony Baxter] How long has that
been going on for?
[Michael Forbes] That's since
last Saturday.
There were big enough there on Friday
and Houston, from Belle road,
he went up and complained,
there was no water up.
They said they would get it
fixed right away.
Well, that's a week now, I've been
waiting and still haven't done it.
I've got the police down and they
won't have nothing to do with it either.
Definitely, if it was other way around
like, if it was me cut off their water,
I would have been charged by now.
I'm really pissed off.
I'm running out of clean clothes.
Dishes are piling up.
You know, you need water.
I've been taking water out of the bottom,
they have a wash in the mornin'.
It's not right...
[grass rustling]
[grunts]
[Molly Forbes] I needed water for the
hens because they drink a lot of water.
My plants outside,
I meant two greenhouses,
so I took the barrel
and we call them a rouser,
the watering can,
and a piece of rope
tied to a pint pot,
and I dipped in
the pint pot in the barn
and filled the rouser and just
threw the barrel back up again
and then Michael said,
”The wee drop coming from
the hose, his hose,
so you'll get some for drinking."
[water splashing]
[Michael Forbes] The toilet's dry.
[water rushing]
This is just another ploy as I said
with Trump to get this before, you know?
It's just, it's not on.
I'm really pissed off as well,
the police is all one-sided, you know.
They say they're not biased,
of course they are.
[laughs]
Yeah.
[Anthony Baxter] You haven't been
down here before?
[Richard] No never, so it's
kind of new territory.
[knocking on door]
10:00am REPORTING AT SITE OFFICE
Trump Golf Course Development
[Anthony Baxter] No, it's locked.
[footsteps]
Hi, I'm Anthony. Anthony, the filmmaker.
- [Paul O'Connor] Oh, yeah.
[Anthony Baxter] This is Richard,
my colleague.
We're just filming with Michael Forbes
this morning and he was saying
that he has not had any water for a week.
[Paul O'Connor] That's right.
There was a problem with the well.
Could I get your information?
[Anthony Baxter] Yeah, no problem.
There you go.
[Paul O'Connor] All that you know
at the moment, is that he's got no water.
[Paul O'Connor] And you're looking
for an angle that may be...
[Anthony Baxter] No, just from work
from facts as they say, not an angle.
[Anthony Baxter] No, it's not an angle.
I'm just trying to work out why...
[Paul O'Connor] Well...
[Anthony Baxter] If Michael is being
without water for a week...
[Paul O'Connor] No, rather than...
- [Anthony Baxter] You know why...
[Paul O'Connor]...the two of us discuss
and get into an argument--
Are you filming at the moment?
[Richard] I am now, yes, sorry.
[Paul O'Connor] Do you mind
not filming here?
[Richard] Okay, I'm sorry.
I thought you were explaining
what was happening.
[Paul O'Connor] There you go.
Good lad.
[Paul O'Connor] Go down
and fix his water then.
[Anthony Baxter] I didn't break it.
$$ - [Paul O'Connor] Well, there you go.
[Anthony Baxter] But you did.
[Paul O'Connor] Yes, so you
leave us to fix it.
[Anthony Baxter] Okay.
$$ - [Paul O'Connor] Anthony, my friend.
[Anthony Baxter] So...
[Paul O'Connor] Michael will have
his water back on,
as soon as we can get it fixed.
[Anthony Baxter] He can't flush
his toilet.
He's got no water coming out of tap.
He's got washing up for a week.
[Paul O'Connor] Yeah, you keep
mentioning a week.
It's just a term of phase?
[Anthony Baxter] Well, he's been
without it for a week?
So, I'm just wondering, does he
have to wait another week for it?
[Paul O'Connor] I don't know.
[Anthony Baxter] But there's somebody
working there now?
[Paul O'Connor] No, not now at
the moment, there isn't.
[Anthony Baxter] Well, why not?
[Paul O'Connor] Because we have
to investigate it first...
to reinstate the man's water.
So it'll be a jewel of a system
and sustain itself.
But hey guys, have a nice day.
It's a lovely day for filming.
All right, okay?
$$ Have you signed in?
[Anthony Baxter] There's nobody
in the office.
[Paul O'Connor] Well, unfortunately,
you won't be able
to sign in today then so,
to get on that site.
You'll suffer
the consequences obviously,
if you break any laws that are in place,
in respect of a construction site.
[Anthony Baxter] Sure, yeah,
absolutely.
I'm not gonna break any laws.
[Paul O'Connor] You're aware of that?
- [Anthony Baxter] Yeah.
[Paul O'Connor] Is that an
expensive camera?
10:30 a.m.
Arrive at Susan Munro's House.
[Anthony Baxter] So, what are we
looking out over here then?
[Susan Munro] Quite a mess now.
We seem to have inherited
a new lake here.
Him, Mr. Trump, I don't know
what he's doing, but he's scraped--
scraped all this.
Oh, here's the police now.
[Anthony Baxter] Police. Ah.
[Susan Munro] We got four
or two of them.
[Michael Forbes] The next thing
was the security guy comes
sneaking around the corner.
I, having told police,
"You were over with Susan Munro?"
And then they just
took off up the road.
And before they went away,
I said to them,
I said, "Who are in charge now?"
And they said, we don't charge
anything. We are the good guys.
[Police] With all due respect, sir.
Would you mind turning the camera off?
[Anthony Baxter] What's it about?
[car engine running]
[Susan Munro] You know, ---.
It's absolutely sickening,
absolutely sickening.
I tell you, I hope they get onto
the environmental health today
because having no water for a week
and no toilets,
no facilities is an absolute disgrace.
They've removed all the topsoil
off the ground.
I mean this is almost
like a flood plain.
As you can see with the bull rushes
and everything, it's just marsh ground
and of course, common sense would tell
you that the water, you know,
flows down to the--
flows down to the sea.
[Anthony Baxter] Yeah.
[Susan Munro] Common sense would
tell anybody that.
So, that's gonna have to be rectified.
I'm not...
Because I see it.
I think environmental health
is an expert to call for them,
but we'll just have to wait
and see what transpires today.
[Police 1] Who's in charge between
the two of you gentlemen?
[Richard] We're just here
as individuals.
What are you here for?
[Police] That's the problem.
Could you state your name please?
[Richard] Why? I think...
[Police] Because there's been
an alleged--
there's been an alleged
breach of peace up
in the estate this morning and as such...
[Susan Munro] Oh, my God.
[Police 1]...we're making inquiries,
so, can I have your name please?
[Richard] My name is Richard Finley.
[Police 1] Okay, and yourself, sir,
could I have your name please?
[Anthony Baxter] Yeah,
I'm Anthony Baxter.
[Susan Munro] And then he just
became more hostile
and more hostile and launched at you.
Gave you no explanation.
[Police 1] What we need to do is--
what we to do now is...
[Anthony Baxter] No, you do not.
[Police 1] You have been detained
under Section 14
at time of pursuit of Scotland
at 1995. Do not--
[Susan Munro] What's he done?
[Anthony Baxter] We just got to...
Richard, grab the camera.
[Police 2] Let go of the camera.
- [Police 1] Let go of the camera.
[Police 2] Before I get it
down myself.
[Anthony Baxter] No, I'm not going to.
I'm not gonna let go of the camera.
I'm sorry.
[Susan Munro] And then
the next thing I knew,
you're wrestling over
the bonnet of Finley's van.
This policeman attacking you,
trying to pull the camera off of you.
Still not giving you any reason
for what you've done.
I think it was totally out of order.
[Anthony Baxter] Don't do that to me!
[Police 2] All right, sir.
You've been detained...
[Susan Munro] Then slammed the handcuffs
on and I saw your wrist,
it was greased and everything
and that was totally out of order.
[Susan Munro] That's disgraceful.
[Anthony Baxter] Will you loosen
these cuffs, please.
[Police 1] Sir, have you got anything...
[Anthony Baxter] Will you loosen
those cuffs, please. They're hurting me.
[Susan Munro] This is a
very sad state of affairs.
[Anthony Baxter] They're
hurting my arms.
[Police 1] Sir, sir,
if you stop shouting.
[Anthony Baxter] Look, will you
just stop doing that to me?!
♪ [music] ♪
[Anthony Baxter] It's 8:30 in
the evening,
I just got back to my car after being
in the police cells for four hours.
We also had our camera confiscated.
Our footage confiscated
by the police.
[Molly Forbes] I think it was Susan
that said, you know,
and I was quite upset about it.
I thought, "Oh gosh, a nice lad
like Anthony being taken into jail."
God, I couldn't sleep.
I thought that, you know?
I thought, "God, who'd like those
Trump people? They're horrish."
[Susan Munro] Two men charged
doing filming at Trump.
I'm sick of seeing this golf
will put Northeast on tourism map.
I don't know what he's
wanting to hide here,
but this keeping people away off
this huge sweat of land is not right.
And then there's that hostile attack
on Anthony for no reason.
The police wouldn't give any reason.
[clicks]
The mess he's making.
Well, there's something.
I mean this is...
I've never seen anything
like this anywhere.
[Anthony Baxter] Does it feel to you
that the police are somehow
working on behalf of Trump?
[Molly Forbes] Oh, definitely,
definitely.
Michael called them to the water
and they just couldn't care less.
[Walter Forbes] It's against the law
to cut out one's water
and if they had damaged it,
supposed it was an accident,
they should have been supplying them
with water, there and then, you know?
Oh, my.
[squawking]
[Female Reporter] On his hit show,
The Apprentice,
Donald Trump's word trumps all
and it appears that power
extends to his business venture
in Scotland, at least for now.
Recently, two British journalists
found themselves arrested
at the site of Mr. Trump's
golf resort near Aberdeen,
which is currently under construction.
[Police] You have been detained
under Section 14
at the time of pursuit of Scotland.
[Paul Holleran] That's quite incredible.
That is just--
that is bullying and harassment.
It really is a shock.
It's an assault on journalists
trying to do their job.
It's completely out of order.
Well, certainly people from around
the world had been taken aback
that this type of thing could happen.
A journalist actually arrested,
violently arrested, handcuffed,
taken to the cells,
having been fingerprinted,
DNA tests and having their equipment
taken off them, kept them in cells.
No, I haven't--
I've never seen it like this.
I know people have been down
for contempt of court and common--
common cold cases and refusing
to expose their source,
but this was just
an interference in journalists
trying to film what really
is a public interest story.
[Walter Forbes] To me, they seem to
just get away with anything they want.
I mean they cut off the water,
but... what will it try next?
Cut off electric? They'll knock down
a pole or something, you know?
Oh, my.
♪ [music] ♪
[Announcer] From New York, the greatest
city in the world,
it's the Late Show
with David Letterman.
Tonight, Donald Trump...
[Donald Trump] It was blowing
very high.
[laughs]
[David Letterman] Now, this
is the guy--
this is the classic story.
Donald Trump, big American comes,
wants to buy up his ranch or his farm
and he says, "Nope."
So, is he gonna sell?
He's not gonna sell?
[Donald Trump] I don't know.
I don't need it.
It's not on the way of what I'm doing.
It's on the outskirts of what I'm doing
and if I buy it,
that will be fine.
[David Letterman] Right.
- [Donald Trump] Nothing I need.
[Michael Forbes] So, they're using me
as an excuse, not to build that hotel.
They're saying
"Oh, it's a nice sewer, a pig sty,"
whatever they want to call it, you know?
But it's our working place, you know?
There's going to be stuff lying about.
I don't throw nothing out because
you never know when it's gonna be handy
and I'm bloody sure no other farmer
would throw anything out either.
[Radio] Anti-Trump campaigners are
warning the Donald Trump Organization
to back off.
One householder refusing to sell
land to the billionaire tycoon
for his golf resort claims diggers
have rolled in regardless
and started to remove his property.
Donald Trump branded
Michael Forbes' farm a slum
and demanded it was cleaned up.
[Michael Forbes] I was sitting in here.
I was on my computer.
I was looking for
parts on my laptops,
and Mickey Foote phoned
in the afternoon and says,
“Do you know there're
diggers on your land?"
So, I had to look out and I saw
the diggers working away.
So, I went to tell my mother
what was going on,
just in case she got excited.
[Molly Forbes] I was disgusted
and felt ill about it.
I mean all that happening
on Michael's land.
That they were going-- wanted to buy?
[Michael Forbes] I took my titled
deed with me and said,
they never even bought,
they never really got it.
And there was two policeman there,
so I went to them.
I shouts, I says,
"Who is the boss here?"
[Molly Forbes] They didn't do
anything about it.
They were guarding them, pulling out
the poles and putting up fences.
[Michael Forbes] And I thought
showing them all the title deeds,
what was mine
and they weren't interested.
They said, "We are just down here
to make sure there's
no damage caused and..."
Bloody damages,
they were ripping up my place.
[camera clicking]
[Michael Forbes] This is the one
that I used to use with my father.
Now, see them busted off.
That was the police that
was supposed to be watching it.
There was no damage done.
It looks to be really irrespectful, huh?
They busted it off.
The spies surely formed
a security here.
They come now.
They've got road man now.
That's my land there.
Not now, that's--
that belongs to them now.
♪ [music] ♪
Now, I've seen enough of this.
This here is the original many salmon
fishing plans and it shows you here
in black and white that this
is the land here for Menie salmon fishers,
but they're sending the papers today
that their plan supercedes my plan.
This here is Trump's plan
of the same area is here
and with this corner cut off.
Michael Forbes gets advice
on the land dispute.
[whirring]
[Andy Wightman] Andy Wightman.
- [Michael Forbes] Mike Forbes.
[Andy Wightman] Good to see you.
Good to see you. Good to see you.
What the bizarre goings on. I'm glad you
could laugh at it at sometimes.
Well, you have to.
- [Michael Forbes] Aye, oh, aye.
[Andy Wightman] You have to, you know.
If you have a dispute with your neighbor
about who's lying to who's,
you seek truce over amicably and
ultimately, you would go to the courts.
You don't grab it. You know,
you don't nakedly grab it.
I mean that's what
they did in the past.
You know, if everyone was to do that,
It would be a state of strife
across the country.
I mean the other thing
is that maps at that time,
were not as accurate as maps are today.
- [Michael Forbes] Yeah, yeah.
[Andy Wightman] So, you know, I thought,
"Well maybe Trump's arguing
about a few meters here and--
- [Michael Forbes] Yeah.
[Andy Wightman] And all the rest of it,
but that's the fact there is a map...
...the fact that it's colored...
...the boundaries are shown clearly.
...and there's a lot land sold with no maps.
- [Michael Forbes] Yeah.
[Andy Wightman] The police are correct
in that where your boundary is,
is not a matter for the police.
- [Michael Forbes] Yeah.
[Andy Wightman] It's not a
criminal matter, the simple of it.
[Michael Forbes] They shouldn't
even be here.
[Andy Wightman] They shouldn't
have been here.
[Andy Wightman] And the fact that Trump
has got a dispute here,
thinks he owns this land,
that's a civil matter.
[Michael Forbes] Before all
that's happened, there was a--
they put on a light and flags,
little red flags.
A little bit pieces of ware
and they put them in here.
I removed them all and I
was charged with theft.
♪ [music] ♪
[Michael Forbes] There was all these
little bloody red flags
all over the place and they
were in danger because my grandsons,
they play bend there
and there were sharp wires.
[Michael Forbes] Twenty seven,
I pulled out of my land.
Twenty seven of these bloody thing.
[Andy Wightman] Is that charged still?
[Michael Forbes] Prosecute at physical
sent a letterbox and dropped it,
but if I do anything like that again,
I will be severely dealt with,
so I'm guilty, you know?
I'm guilty and I would have
preferred if it went to court.
[Andy Wightman] I mean to me
that suggests, you know,
double standard and very,
very political policing.
[Anthony Baxter] Have you ever
come across a case like this?
[Andy Wightman] No, no, no.
This is unprecedented.
♪ [music] ♪
[leaves rustling]
[Michael Forbes] That's a bit stupid,
isn't it?
They've left an axis there, look.
Where does it go?
Nowhere.
How can he say that's
better than nature?
[laughing]
Boy, the man lives
in his cuckoo land, huh?
[Andy Wightman] That flag
stands for freedom
and for a country that you
are passionate about, presumably.
[Michael Forbes] I used to be.
I used to be until someone gave them
the right to destroy their bloody links.
[Michael Forbes] I voted for SMP
for 35 years.
I'll never vote
for them again, never.
They've done this country wrong.
They're giving it away to the Americans.
[laughs]
[Male Reporter] American tycoon,
Donald Trump, has just been to Aberdeen
ahead of receiving an honorary degree
from the city's Robert Gordon University.
[Male Reporter] This afternoon,
the tripping of Trump campaign handed in
a 6-1/2 thousand signature petition
against the University's decision.
[Susan Munro] It's really quite sad
to see what he's doing.
I thought it was gonna be done
with a little tweak here and there
but it's-- it's not.
It's just been flattened,
especially the bit beside us
and he's just moving south.
Awful that or-- You know, our country
have let him take an SSI and not--
and I'm sure he's having a quick
smile to himself, you know.
Tour of Golf Course No.1.
Invited Media only.
[Susan Munro] They're swarm
around here like flies,
whenever he's here and I mean
it's just a joke.
I also think it's just
so false, you know.
All these people arrive
and suited and booted
and "Yes, Mr. Trump.
No Mr. Trump."
What's he done here to deserve
this and destroy this site,
a special scientific interest
and a beautiful dune system.
[Anthony Baxter] Sarah?
[Security] Can you head
back off please?
It's invite only.
If you can just head back off.
Turn your camera off.
[Anthony Baxter] Mr. Trump,
I was wondering if
I could ask you a couple of questions?
[Donald Trump] The people love
what we're doing.
They love that I'm spending hundreds
of millions of pounds on doing it.
They love the fact that
I'm creating a lot of jobs.
[Susan Munro] Mr. Trump
doesn't appreciate
just how much the system moves.
Some of these things will never come back
because the conditions
will be totally changed.
All these damn chemicals
on the greens and...
Oh, me.
You just wonder if it's
going to end with this.
♪ [music] ♪
[Susan Munro] The last time
he was here,
he made quite a rather sour comment
about myself and Finley
and the dog, you know,
demonstrators.
And I thought, I'm not a demonstrator.
I said I live here.
♪ [music] ♪
[Dr. David Kennedy] This one
was from the students.
I mean any gift from the students,
I always valued.
Because I thought that was what
my work was about.
From the moment I decided that I was
going to hand my honorary degree back,
my thoughts were all about
how I could get maximum publicity
because I knew that simply handing it
back in a private manner,
it would simply put away
and that would be the end of it.
[Reporter] How difficult is it
for you to return this degree?
[Dr. David Kennedy] It's not
difficult at all.
I'm going to march in that door and ask
whether the principal is available.
If he isn't, it will be given into
the desk and that will be it
because somebody's got to
stand up for these people
and to make sure that the world
knows there are people
who don't approve of this.
I don't approve of bullying.
I don't approve of bullying
to the people on their Menie estate.
That is my honorary degree certificate.
Not wanted, not wanted.
[applause]
[Reporter] For someone in such
a significant and serious position
to take what is very obvious,
a very personal and determined stance
is a very positive thing for us
and we are here
in pure support of Dr. Kennedy
and his position.
[Dr. David Kennedy] Donald Trump
have said--
he thinks, "You cannot be too greedy."
He believes that you should be
brutal and powerful.
He believes that sacking people
is not a bad thing.
He had boasted off the number
of people he's sacked.
These are not a sort of qualities
I would expect of a man
who were to receive
an honorary degree.
[applause]
[Audrey Kennedy] He feels very strongly
and I think under those circumstances,
it isn't a difficult decision to make.
[Reporter] David, what happened inside?
[Dr. David Kennedy] Well, Professor
Harbor wasn't available and so,
I saw one of the Vice Principals,
but of course, she's following
the party line that Mr. Trump
is a very successful entrepreneur.
He's a billionaire and of course,
that tells you everything.
[Radio] "You're making
a mockery of the system,"
words of Dr. David Kennedy,
who's handed back his honorary degree
to Robert Gordon University and he
has this message for the tycoon.
[Dr. David Kennedy] "Don't trump
along our neighbors.
Don't destroy the environment of Aberdeen.
This is part of the jewels of
Scotland that are being destroyed.
My view is take your money elsewhere.
We don't want it."
Degree day.
Robert Gordon University, Aberdeen.
[Martin Glegg] It's opposed to people,
but it's letting people know the truth
because we feel that people
just don't know the realities
of this development and if they did know,
they'd think twice.
There's some people in Aberdeen that
really want this development to go ahead.
Half of people and they're not letting
the word out on what's going on.
[Charles Skene] But have you
been out at many houses?
[Martin Glegg] Yes, a lot.
[Charles Skene] And have you seen some
of ramshackle dumpsters around there?
[Martin Glegg] If you're referring
to Michael Forbes'--
[Charles Skene] I'm not referring
to any specific.
I'm talking in general terms.
Have you seen it?
[Martin Glegg] Ah, I've been
to many, yes.
[Charles Skene] Here's the point.
You take in wealthy people
from all over the world, flying in
in the plain there and they're looking
at houses that are in bad condition
with ramshackle tractors
and all farm implements
lying over there,
do you think that does any good
to the-- to the vision of Scotland?
♪ [bagpipe music] ♪
[Female Reporter] American billionaire
Donald Trump, defied his critics
to pick up an honorary degree from
Aberdeen's Robert Gordon University.
He's pledged to build the world's
greatest golf course
on the Menie estate in Aberdeenshire.
[Male Reporter] Today,
Aberdeen's Robert Gordon University,
recognized US tycoon Donald Trump's
ability to make money,
now a doctor of
business administration.
[Reporter] Are these cutting short
against the railing would be quite nice?
[Donald Trump] How about this?
- [Reporter] Lovely.
[Security] Stay here.
Excuse me.
[cameras clicking]
[Reporter] Can we get with your
face again, Mr. Trump?
[cameras clicking]
Thank you very much.
[Donald Trump] Hello, everybody.
[Reporter] Is the course in schedule?
[Donald Trump] Yeah, the course
is in perfect schedule.
In fact if anything, it's ahead of
schedule and I am very happy to report
that everything we've done, I think,
it's even coming out better
than we had anticipated
in our wildest dreams.
It's going to be really spectacular.
There doesn't seem to be people
against the job.
The only one I see
is this gentleman right here,
who I've never seen before until
yesterday, when he started screaming.
Question? Real journalist,
I want real journalist.
[Anthony Baxter] Mr. Trump, I wonder
what you would say to Dr. David Kennedy.
He handed back his degree last week
and said that your honor
was an insult to decent people everywhere
and also accused you of bullying people
on the Menie estate and I mean,
I myself, have been arrested,
handcuffed and put in a prison cell
for four hours, whilst
interviewing your representative,
Mr. Paul O'Connor on the site.
I just wondered whether you felt
that was the right way to treat people
and whether in fact,
you had anything to hide?
[Donald Trump] I never
heard of Mr. Kennedy.
I don't who he is,
so I can't really refer--
I mean you're asking me about
a person that I've never heard of.
[Anthony Baxter] Dr. David Kennedy,
the former principal of...
[Donald Trump] I've never heard of him,
I'm sorry.
This is a very popular job.
It's only questions like you ask,
that, you know, cause trouble.
Any other questions?
[Anthony Baxter] Yes, Mr. Trump.
I just wondered if you could
tell us how many local people are...
[Sarah Malone] One question
per journalist.
[Anthony Baxter]...how many local people
are employed on the site at the moment?
[Donald Trump] A lot, we have
a lot of local people employed...
[Anthony Baxter] Can you
give us a number?
[Donald Trump] And we're
just beginning. I don't have numbers.
We're just beginning, but a lot of
people and there will be more and more.
We've had hundreds of people
doing the marring.
Now, we're ready to start
the marring again.
That's a very big project,
but we've got a lot of local people
employed on the site.
[Anthony Baxter] But it is
an Irish contractor?
The following week.
David Milne's house.
[David Milne] So, I'm gonna go
and find the police shortly
and let them know, take it from there.
I've also spoken to the lawyer.
I'm phoning in connection
with an instant number
you already have on your books,
instant 56 of the 18th of October,
in other words, yesterday.
Well, it was regarding,
we expected some persons come
onto our land yesterday
and cut down and remove a fence.
That didn't happen. However,
they have come on today
and cut down and removed our fence.
This is the letter
that we received.
They're saying that I have a fence
and part of a shed or other building
erected on land belonging to them.
They're saying that they now
intend to remove the fence.
You'll notice I'm not given the option
to remove it myself and that they may,
if they choose, put the fence
marked up on their drawing.
Donald Trump, Jr.
As far as the shed goes,
they're giving me 72 hours
or they're gonna raise an action
in the sheriff court to have it removed.
If you take the double garages
sitting here, okay?
I have a stick shed sits here.
There's an old brick shed
from the coast guard days
that sits there and the house
actually sits in about here.
Out here, there is a pole
for the overhead electricity line.
They are claiming at the moment,
that this boundary actually
runs something like that.
And here, they're trying to
take a back wall off my garage.
[Donald Trump] We've been very nice.
We have tried to be very nice.
We actually just learned that one of them
may have built their house on our land.
We learned that last night
when we were doing a survey.
One of the people actually have
a big chunk of their house on our land,
so we're having that checked out.
[Anthony Baxter] Who was that,
Mr. Trump?
[Donald Trump] You'll find out.
[David Milne] I've come home today,
I see the fence is missing.
That's the police car
that was in here this morning,
which makes it 8, 9,
10 o'clock this morning earlier by,
so it'll be interesting to see
what time the fence actually came down.
They hit the power line yesterday,
240 volts supplied to my house.
[Susan Munro] Mr. Trump's workmen
severed the line with the digger
and popped line and of course,
everything shorted
and it cut everybody off.
[David Milne] And it's working
the way quite the thing.
There you go, power went out.
Not only is it in my opinion,
criminal damage or vandalism,
but now they've also committed theft
by removing it from my lot,
which if you care to remember
is precisely,
what they charged Michael Forbes with,
when he removed marker poles
from the site.
David Milne receives a bill
for a new boundary fence
put up by Trump contractors.
The fence that they put up
without my permission.
The attached invoice is now due.
Please arrange payment
for half of this invoice.
2820 pounds to be made payable to Trump
International Golf Lengths Scotland.
♪ [music] ♪
[Susan Munro] I come out
of my bed this morning.
The whole house shaking,
things falling off in my shelf,
but this is getting bigger
by the day, so it's incredibly high now.
[Anthony Baxter] Did you ask the
builders what they're doing with this?
[Susan Munro] Finley did.
- [Anthony Baxter] What did they say?
[Susan Munro] It's Mr. Trump's
instructions?
[Anthony Baxter] Mr. Trump's
[Susan Munro] Yeah.
[Anthony Baxter] To put all this
earth in?
[Susan Munro] Yeah, yeah,
to block our view.
To harass us, obviously. There are no
bank on the plants, anything like that.
Oh, I don't know what to do.
♪ [music] ♪
[Walter Forbes] I don't know
what it's for.
I don't know even know
what the mound it molds for.
It's harassment for David Milne up here.
They pushed the mold off the field...
...to block off his view or whatever.
What did they do it there?
They had a whole field that they
could have put the mold in.
♪ [music] ♪
[David Milne] It's rather meaningless.
It took them maybe
a week to 10 days
to actually construct, so there's
quite a lot of work involved,
there's a lot of time involved,
there's a lot of effort involved
for no real purpose.
[Donald Trump] Get it done
and don't spend a lot.
[Voiceover] It's all on
Donald J. Trump's Fabulous World of Golf.
[Donald Trump] Sarah, I wanna
get rid of that house.
[Sarah Malone] It's going to create
a bit of a stir.
[Donald Trump] Who cares, who cares?
You know what? Who cares?
It's our property.
We can do what we want.
We're trying to build
the greatest course in the world.
This house is ugly.
There are some houses quite far away
from the course but nevertheless,
they are in view, but we are berming
some of the areas,
so that you don't see the houses.
I don't want to see the houses and
nobody has a problem with it, I guess.
Maybe the people that live
in the houses have.
[truck engine running]
[Susan Munro] There's a great,
big point here.
Now, the more muffler scrape
and the water is all bubbling up.
Well, I was just waiting for that.
- [Anthony Baxter] Ah, water.
[Susan Munro] Yeah,
water table the fitter.
It's supposed to be a putting green
while I could cook,
well, I suppose you'd have to cook
with a putting green.
Not that like balls flying in my garden,
but we've come today.
"We're making a car park."
No, you're not,
it's not in your plans.
That big mound in front of us,
that shouldn't have been done,
not on the plans, because there're
just the dunes there, it came a bit,
we used to walk over onto the beach.
I took photos on Anthony's camera.
I mean we got a shock.
We just stood and looked around.
Totally flat sand everywhere.
Everything gone.
♪ [music] ♪
Total devastation.
[Susan Munro] I'm just trying
not to get you guys in.
I'm just trying to swing round.
And just get the vastness of the...
...what he's done.
♪ [music] ♪
All that sand that's lying down there.
I mean they're driving it from away
along at the sand dunes of Balmedie.
I didn't think they'd be allowed
to move the sand along to here.
They just seem to please themselves.
They don't follow the plans.
No, no.
♪ [music] ♪
[David Letterman] I'm imagining
how beautiful it must be,
these dunes on the beautiful coast of
Scotland, the west coast of Scotland?
[Donald Trump] Well, yes.
More or less.
[David Letterman] Yeah, and
what do you mean more or less?
[laughter]
[Donald Trump] It's such a big area,
it covers a lot of earth in.
Everywhere I go, I love to build.
[David Letterman] It's
so beautiful to build.
[Donald Trump] It is beautiful,
but I'll make it more beautiful.
Actually when I finish,
it will be far more beautiful.
[David Letterman] Really?
18th Hole. The Old Course.
I'm not fond of Donald Trump
and I wouldn't want to come all this way
to go play a new course
nor one of his facility courses,
so I'm not sure that it's gonna be
a very successful operation.
You know, he's pretty goddy.
I mean that is the way he does things
and he's a New Yorker and so, I'm sure
it will be a spectacular course.
I'm not sure if it will fit in
with you know, tradition itself.
[Anthony Baxter] He says,
it's gonna be the best in the world.
Well, Donald would say that,
wouldn't he, you know?
Trump will price it, most
likely outside of my range.
♪ [music] ♪
[Prof. Paul Chesire] Of course,
it will be some local workers.
The question is what proportion of
workers will be local and there I think,
that the estimates that are made
in the economic impact study,
are widely optimistic.
I mean if I'm Irish,
I'd be delighted if Irish workers
would be employed.
If I were Polish, I'm delighted
the Polish are being employed,
but they're not going to be creating jobs
in the local economy and indeed,
migrant workers tend to remit
a lot of their wages
back to where they come from,
so nobody would be spending
within the local economy.
If a British developer came along,
saying that they wanted to build
500 houses and 450
bed hotel on an area
of wild beauty remote
from any large city,
which was going to destroy
what is the most highly protected
type of site we have, a site of special
scientific interest,
which was, by all accounts
a unique type of site.
They will be laughed out of court.
Think of Mr. Trump as a poker player
and he's got a hand, but he's also
bluffing the local authorities
and Scottish government
to give him planning permission.
That planning permission is immensely,
immensely valuable.
Thousands of millions of pounds probably,
just to get the planning permission.
So, his job is to persuade people
that this huge economic benefits.
That's his job, but we should be
critically cautious in accepting numbers
which come from the Trump camp.
[Anthony Baxter] And from what
you've seen of those numbers,
do you think there
has been enough caution?
[Prof. Paul Chesire] No, I don't think
there's been enough caution in
critically interpreting those numbers.
It's all surprising that sort
of city farmers might be deceived
by glamorous international superstar,
like Donald Trump.
I do find it more surprising
that the Scottish government,
I thought was quite canny, has full
enforcement in the way they have.
♪ [bagpipe music] ♪
The March of Menie. Supporters walk
to Michael Forbes home.
[Susan Munro] This is the pond
where all the ducks were.
I don't know what they've done,
but they've now, as you can see,
got this fence up
with this orange netting.
♪ [music] ♪
[Martin Ford] Horrifying of course,
to see the-- you know,
the sand just piled up
like that willy nilly.
This was a pristine and a fantastic
dune system and now,
parts of it are in the process
of being wrecked
and that's very sad and that
things stand at the moment.
Much of the rest of it
is going to be wrecked as well.
♪ [bagpipe music] ♪
[indistinct chattering]
♪ [music] ♪
[Michael] My name's Michael.
I'm stopping by the plaza today,
just offering you some support.
[Michael Forbes] Excellent.
Thank you.
[Michael] Good luck.
[Michael Forbes] Hi, how are you doing?
[David McCue] I'm here
to offer you support.
[Sheila Forbes] Thank you.
Thank you very much.
[indistinct shouting]
Come and join us.
Join us.
[Dr. Kennedy] It's good to see that
there's so many young people here,
supporting justice
and I'm at one with them.
I agree completely and I find it
very, very, very pleasing to see
so many people turning out today
in order to support the people,
who had been victimized by Donald Trump
and his profit-making ways.
[Michael Forbes] I'm very proud, yeah.
It gives you a boost.
It really gives you a boost.
You know, when I'm down in--
down in the mouth about
what's going on here
and then you get all these people
that's supporting you.
It's really good.
Yeah, I'm really proud.
[Anthony Baxter] What kind
of things they have been saying?
[Michael Forbes] Just keep up the faith.
It's always the same every time
to keep up the faith
and I'm doing my best.
[laughing]
Yeah.
♪ [music] ♪
[Molly Forbes] We're going up to the
Justice hall to have a cup of tea.
♪ As I was walking,
across the Marram grass ♪
♪ I saw a notice, it said
"No trespass" ♪
♪ On the other side,
I wrote "up Trump's ass" ♪
♪ This land is made for me not you. ♪
♪ This land is my land,
this land ain't your land ♪
♪ from Caledonia to Channel Islands ♪
[indistinct singing]
Local Hero (1983)
[Bartender] Can I help you, gentlemen?
[Mac] Ah, yes.
I'd like to use the telephone,
is there one in the hotel?
[Bartender] There's a phone booth
just across the road at the Getty.
You'll need some change.
[Bartender] You can talk to anyone
anywhere in the world from there.
Could you change this for me, please?
Tens the lot?
[Bartender] Well, now, I don't think
we'll manage that.
Hey, you got any change, lads?
The gentleman here would like to make
a very important long distant
phone call, intercontinental.
Hey, come on, give me your change.
[coins jingle]
[phone ringing]
[Female Speaker] Trump Organization.
[Anthony Baxter] Oh, hello there.
Yes, I was wondering if I could speak
to Donald Trump, please?
I'm calling from Scotland
just recording this call.
My name is Anthony Baxter.
[Female Speaker] Okay, but what
was regarding this?
[Anthony Baxter] Yes, I'm making a
documentary about the Trump golf course
down in North Aberdeen
and just wondering
whether I can speak to him about it, so...
[Female Speaker] Could you give me
an e-mail to check?
[Anthony Baxter] Yeah, I did e-mail
a few times actually last year.
I did...
[Female Speaker] Are you sure you have
the correct e-mail address?
[Anthony Baxter] Oh, I think so,
because she returned the e-mail saying
that he was too busy to do
an interview at that time,
so I just thought I'd touch base...
[Anthony Baxter] Right,
I didn't do that
and then I didn't hear anything back.
I mean I don't mind waiting
for a meeting to finish,
it's just that I've only got
so many 50 Ps here.
And I can't just speak
to Mr. Trump's PA.
[Female Speaker] Hold on a moment.
- [Anthony Baxter] Okay.
[coins jingling]
[Anthony Baxter] Okay, thanks.
[Female Speaker] Hello?
- [Anthony Baxter] Hello.
[Female Speaker] Okay, sir. I'm sorry,
but that's the only possibility,
is to e-mail [inaudible].
Thank you, sir.
I'm sorry.
I have to take other calls.
[tone beeps]
[car engine starts]
TWO MONTHS AFTER THE MARCH OF MEINE,
DONALD TRUMP TOLD AN ABERDEEN NEWSPAPER
HE WOULD NOT SEEK COMPULSORY
PURCHASE ORDERS TO REMOVE
RESIDENTS FROM THEIR HOMES.
MR. TRUMP THEN ANNOUNCED HE WAS
CONSIDERING STANDING AS A
PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATE
IN THE UNITED STATES.
IN JUNE 2012, MR. TRUMP THREATENED
TO ABANDON HIS PROMISE TO BUILD
A GOLF COURSE HOTEL, SAYING A PROPOSED
OFFSHORE WIND FARM WOULD SPOIL THE VIEW.
♪ [music] ♪
[Martin Ford] I have to say,
they're all excellent pictures.
They really are very good
and I love the idea of placing them
on well-known works of art.
[Molly Forbes] I was quite tired
by the time I did get them all together.
[laughter]
And I was stunned, well.
♪ [music] ♪
[Martin Ford] I think I like Michael
and Sheila best.
It's very close to the painting
on which he had spaced,
and I'm also wondering what Michael's
contemplating doing with that fork.
♪ [music] ♪